Kasthuri Kannan, PhD

Associate Professor, UT MD Anderson Cancer Center

kskannan@mdanderson.org (551) 284 9106

• 2130 W Holcombe Blvd. Houston. TX 77494

♦ https://kannan-kasthuri.github.io/ ■ US Citizen

in linkedin.com/in/kasthuri-kannan-0a05b43

PROFILE

Data scientist with 15 years experience primarily working in cancer research. Recogonized for managing and hands-on approach with large-scale data, statistical modeling, and image processing. A team player.

Actively seeking an opportunity to excel in an industrial setting.

EDUCATION

Doctor of Philosophy (Computer Science)

College Station, Texas

Texas A&M University

Master of Science (Mathematics)

2000 – 2002

Texas A&M University

College Station, Texas

Master of Science (Mathematics)

1998 - 2000

Indian Institute of Technology, Madras

Chennai, India

2002 - 2008

Bachelor of Science (Mathematics)

1995 - 1998

University of Madras

Chennai, India

SKILLS

Leadership

Data Science/Machine Learning/AI

Managing data science and bioinformatics projects

Software (Representative)

Python, R, Java, Cypher, SQL, Bioinformatics tools, Unix, HPC, Neo4j, MySQL, PostgreSQL, HTML, CSS, Javascript, APOC, GDS (Neo4j), Spatstat

Math, CS, Statistics and Programming Ethical hacking, Domain knowledge, LLMs

Bioinformatics & Image Processing Pipeline development and data engineering Geospatial analysis

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

UT MD Anderson Cancer Center

02/2020 - present Houston, TX

Associate Professor

- Leading graph database development for multi-omics data integration
- Establishing spatial modeling of pathology images using R spatstat
- Supervising post-doctoral fellows and students

New York University

11/2013 - 08/2019 New York, NY

Assistant Professor • Established bioinformatics pipelines and investigated cancer datasets

- Directed and taught data science and machine learning courses

Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center

Research Fellow/Associate

• Established mutation pipeline for Brain/Head & Neck cancers

Discovered ATRX mutations in lower grade gliomas

• Provided directed insights in various cancer studies through data analysis

Pennsylvania State University

Research Associate

Organized data analysis pipelines

· Offered bioinformatics consultation to researchers

Managed sequencing tasks

Stowers Institute for Medical Research

Research Specialist II

Developed image processing methods for worm and fly tracking

• Implemented an automated data workflow to process yeast cell images

• Responsible for high quality image acquistion and microscope maintanence

Knowledge Based Systems, Inc

Internship

• Delivered data driven directed insights for aircraft movement operations

Proposed cost and time saving measures for managing air force logistics

01/2008 - 09/2010

01/2007 - 12/2008

College Station, TX

ACTIVE DATA SCIENCE PROJECTS

Geospatial modeling of tissues — Spatial point processes are powerful statistical frameworks for studying point patterns. By representing cells as points and annotating the measurements taken on those cells, such as gene expression at single cell level, it is appropriate to study their interactions using point processes. We extensively use spatstat, an R package, to model interactions and derive directed insights in cancers.

Biomarker discovery using graph database — Graph databases can help identify biomarkers by efficiently representing complex biological networks. By enabling powerful queries and community detection algorithms, graph databases make exploring the relationships between multiple genes easier, thus facilitating the discovery of potential biomarkers critical for diagnostics or therapeutic targets. We use Neo4j, a property graph database, and algorithms from the Graph Data Science Library (GDS) to derive insights and propose actionable biological targets.

Biomarker validation using Graph Convolution Networks (GCNs) — Insilico validation of biomarkers is critical for providing actionable biological targets for experiments and prognosis. We apply graph convolutional networks to validate critical biomarkers discovered through the graph database. GCNs enhance biomarker discovery by leveraging the structure of biological networks, such as gene-gene interactions, and learning meaningful node/edge representations. By aggregating information from a node's neighbors, GCNs capture local and global patterns, allowing the model to predict relationships between genes and diseases more effectively.

INVITED TALKS (REPRESENTATIVE)

Mayo Clinic (2023), National University of Singapore (2022), Texas A&M University (2021), Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences (2019), Institute of Mathematical Sciences, w/ honorarium (2018)

PUBLICATIONS

Published 32 peer reviewed articles, that includes very high-impact journals. Please refer https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/?term=kasthuri+kannan&sort=date&sort_order=desc ☑

04/2011 - 10/2013 New York, NY

10/2010 - 03/2011 State College, PA

Kansas City, MO